Guide to the Gove Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Gove family papers
1788-1870
1842-1859
WA MSS S-1302
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.25
(1 box)
The papers contain correspondence and other papers documenting Gove family life and the experiences of Josiah E. Gove in gold rush California.
Gove family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were purchased in 1957 from Peter Decker on the William Robertson Coe Fund for Western Americana.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Gove Family Papers document the lives of Josiah E. Gove, a gold miner and entrepreneur in California, and his immediate Massachusetts family. The papers span the dates 1788 to 1870, but the bulk of material covers the period 1842 to 1859.
Luke and Harriet Gove, with their two children, Josiah E. and Angie, moved to Stowe, Massachusetts in 1842 to open a boarding house. In 1848 the family moved to Lowell, where Luke and Josiah actively participated in the Sons of Temperance. Josiah moved to Boston in 1849 and in 1850 sailed around Cape Horn to California on the Edward Everett. While in California, Josiah corresponded with his parents, sister, and cousins, H. C. Neese and O. C. Neese. He tried several business ventures, including gold mining, operating a store, and running pack mules. Josiah's cousin "French," the son of Luke's sister Betsey and John Paige, occasionally worked with him. In 1856 Josiah was elected justice of the peace for Butte County, California, but by 1859 he had experienced severe financial losses and suffered from poor health. With the financial support and encouragement of his parents, he made arrangements to return to Lowell.
Josiah's letters are concerned with his sea voyage to California, staking mining claims on the Feather River, and difficulties of starting a business. Luke Gove's correspondence focuses on his desire for Josiah to return home and on the general well-being of the family. The initiation ceremony and practices of the Sons of Temperance in Lowell are referred to in Luke's January 1848 letter to his sister Betsey Paige. Angie Gove discusses her schooling, music lessons, and social events. In O. C. Neese's 1854 letter to Josiah, she tells of her plight as an unmarried woman and the arrangements made for her to live with Luke and Harriet Gove.
Families; Frontier and pioneer life -- California; Gold mines and mining -- California; Temperance; Butte County (Calif.); California -- Gold discoveries; California -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; Gold miners -- California; Gove, Josiah E.; Gove, Luke; Gowen family
- Box and Folder List, 1842-48
  - Correspondence, 1842-48 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1849-50 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1852-53 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1854-55 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1856-70 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Gove, Angie, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Gove, Harriet, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Gove, H. N., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Gove, Josiah E., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Gove, Luke, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - M. C. J. and "Daniel" (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Paige, Betsey, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bills and receipts, 1788-1867 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Justice of the Peace appointment, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous envelopes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)